<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two precious and divine antidotes against the plague of pestilence; or any other judgement incident vnto vs Giving excellent instructions and comforts vnto all that well vse them in time of neede. The first prescribing holy preservatiues against this, or any other plague: written by a Christian and charitable well-willer vnto his countrey. The second, setting downe sweete consolations for such as be visited by the plague: written by a famous, learned, and faithfull pastour, vnto some of his flocke in the time of their visitations.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20390</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854040</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854040</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19446</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20390)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19446)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 575:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two precious and divine antidotes against the plague of pestilence; or any other judgement incident vnto vs Giving excellent instructions and comforts vnto all that well vse them in time of neede. The first prescribing holy preservatiues against this, or any other plague: written by a Christian and charitable well-willer vnto his countrey. The second, setting downe sweete consolations for such as be visited by the plague: written by a famous, learned, and faithfull pastour, vnto some of his flocke in the time of their visitations.</title>
                  <author>S. P., fl. 1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12, 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Dawson] for Nathanael Nevvbery,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The second antidote is signed at end: Your loving pastour, S.P.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19446:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19446:1"/>
            <p> TWO PRECIOVS AND DIVINE ANTIDOTES againſt the Plague of <hi>Peſtilence;</hi> or any other judgement incident vnto vs. Giving excellent Inſtructions and Comforts vnto all that well vſe them in time of Neede. The firſt preſcribing holy Preſervatiues againſt this, or any other PLAGVE: <hi>Written by a Chriſtian and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble well-willer vnto his Countrey.</hi> The ſecond, Setting downe ſweete Conſolations for ſuch as be viſited by <hi>the</hi> Plague: <hi>Written by a famous, learned, and faithfull Paſtour, vnto ſome of his flocke in the time of their viſitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for NATHANAEL NEVVBERY. 1625.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19446:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19446:2"/>
            <head>An <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt the <hi>Plague,</hi> or any other Iudgement incident to this NATION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſayd of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> that they <note place="margin">Iudg. 18.</note> were a <hi>ſecure people and dwelt careleſſe:</hi> poore ſilly ſoules, they never dreamed of any harme, till the beeſome of deſtruction came and ſwept them all away. It is ſayd like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the old world; that <hi>they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 38.</note> 
               <hi>eate, they dranke, they married and were given in marriage;</hi> they gaue themſelues wholly to iovialitie and mirth, living ſo here as if they ſhould haue lived here for ever; never conſidering, that <hi>the reioycing of the wicked is ſhort, and the ioy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob. 20. 5. Iob. 21. 13.</note> 
               <hi>of hypocrites is but for a moment;</hi> That <hi>they ſpend their dayes in mirth and iollitie and ſodainly goe downe to the graue:</hi> they lay in a dead ſleepe, drowned in a deepe ſecuritie, till a fearefull <note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> and vniverſall Deluge came out from the Lord, and drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them all: onely <hi>waking Noah</hi> was wonderfully preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Arke. I would I could not ſay of our Nation as it was ſayd of <hi>Laiſh:</hi> wee are a ſecure and careleſſe people; I would theſe Scriptures were not this day fulfilled in our eares; but alas it is more then manifeſt, wee are a Nation drowned in ſecuritie; this is the fruit of our long proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; wee are <hi>at eaſe in Sion,</hi> wee <hi>ſit every man vnder his owne vine and vnder his fig tree,</hi> therefore we ſing a <hi>Requiem</hi> vnto our ſoules, and ſay, <hi>We ſhall haue peace though we walke after our owne luſts;</hi> wee ſhall never be mooved: <hi>Soule take</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 19 20</note> 
               <hi>thy reſt, thou haſt much goods layd vp for many yeares, eate, drinke, and take thy pleaſure, let thy heart cheare thee,</hi> be iovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19446:3"/> and merry; but alas poore ſoules they never conſider, that <hi>this night their ſoules ſhall be taken away from them; That for all theſe things the Lord will bring them to iudgement;</hi> they <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11. 9.</note> put farre from them the evill day. But in this ſleepie and drowſie age, I doubt not but there be ſome <hi>waking Noahs,</hi> who if they cannot prevaile for others, yet at leaſt build an Arke for the ſafety of their owne ſoules: in this cold and frozen age, doubtleſſe there be ſome <hi>zealous Moyſeſſes,</hi> who <hi>ſtand in the gap</hi> between God and his people, and hold Gods hand from ſmiting by their vnceſſant prayers: though <hi>Aegypt</hi> be full of darkeneſſe, yet there is <hi>ſome light in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhen;</hi> ſome that ſhine as lights though the whole world lye in darkeneſſe: though the world be full of folly and the moſt part runne on as fooles, and are puniſhed, yet queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe there be ſome prudent men that learne to foreſee the evill to come and hide themſelues. <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>God hath given to this Nation of ours many a faire war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as loath to ſmite, till needs he muſt: he hath ſent his Miniſters early and late to thunder in our eares; yet except we doe repent, we ſhall all likewiſe periſh, judgement will come: he hath ſet our neighbours houſe on fire as a beacon to giue vs warning, I meane, the judgements that haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen our brethren beyond the Seas: he hath ſent many ſmall judgements before, as forerunners of that great one to come; as little gunſhots before the great murthering peece: It hath beene told vs before, that if we repented not God would doe ſuch a thing in <hi>England,</hi> that whoſoever ſhould heare thereof, <hi>both his eares ſhould tingle;</hi> thus the Cockes crowed before the ſtorme, but we regarded it not: God hath now ſent a fearefull plague amongſt vs as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther warning more heavie then the former, and if this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not moue vs to repent, we may ſtill looke for heavier, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it; <hi>I will yet puniſh them</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit. 26.</note> 
               <hi>ſeven times more,</hi> and if that will not doe <hi>ſeven times more;</hi> the Lord will not ceaſe to ſmite, ſo long as wee ceaſe not to ſinne; he hath more ſcourges then one; if the preſent <hi>Plague</hi> will not doe, famine ſhall, if famine will not doe, the ſword
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19446:3"/> ſhall vtterly cut vs off from being a Nation. I beſeech yee my brethren conſider it, even with teares I beſeech yee: what a woefull ſpectacle will it be to ſee our ſtreetes ſwim with the bloud of vs all, to ſee our women raviſhed, and their little infants daſhed againſt the ſtones; to ſee the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and abominable Maſſe ſet vp in our Churches, to ſee all turned topſie turvie, vpſide downe; whoſe heart doth not yearne and even melt within him, to thinke on theſe things: oh conſider the fearefull deſolation that befell <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> the whole Booke.</note> and the grievous calamities comne vpon our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren beyond the Seas, they were God his people as well as we: oh that we could be warned by other mens harmes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>But what haue I done (ſayth</hi> England) <hi>that ſuch things as theſe ſhould befall mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Behold, thou haſt requited the Lord evill for good: God hath given thee the glorious light of his bleſſed Goſpell to be Preached plentifully for threeſcore yeare together; he diſpelled the miſts and clouds of Popery and ſuperſtition, and cauſed this cleare light to ſhine; he hath committed to thee his ſtatutes and his covenants; he hath not dealt ſo with every Nation: he hath given thee many great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious deliverances, the like never heard of, eſpecially thoſe of the <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Eighty-eight:</hi> then thou dideſt promiſe better obedience: he hath given thee long peace and quietneſſe, no noiſe of Warre hath beene heard in thy ſtreetes: he hath given thee plentie and proſperitie, a land flowing with milke and hony, even all that heart can wiſh: he hath made thee even a Mirrour and a Wonderment to the whole world for his manifold bleſſings. But how haſt thou now requited thy God, O <hi>England?</hi> 1. with ignorance not onely compelled but affected; <hi>Light is come into the world, but men loue darkeneſſe rather then light:</hi> 2. with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Goſpell, a crying bloudy ſinne, a ſinne never heard of among the <hi>Iewes:</hi> 3. with Blaſphemy of all ſorts, ſwearing, forſwearing, taking God his great and dreadfull name in vaine, nothing more rife even in the mouthes of children that can but newly ſpeake: 4. with prophanation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19446:4"/> of the Sabbath, ſpending it in ſports and idle paſtimes. In thee is ſecretly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted that <hi>curſed</hi> ſin of <hi>Idolatry:</hi> in thee is Atheiſme, drunkenneſſe, rioting, feaſting, when the Lord calls for faſting: in thee are diſobedient to parents, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of authoritie, deſpiſers of God his meſſengers, diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of equalls; in thee are murtherers, even Soule-mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers; contentious perſons, whoremongers, adulterers; in thee is Bribery, Oppreſſion, Vſury, Simony, fraud and couſenage; Iuſtice and Truth is periſhed from thy Land: in thee is lying, tale-bearing, falſe witneſſe-bearing, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, pride, idleneſſe, fulneſſe of bread, deepe ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, even all the ſinnes of <hi>Sodome:</hi> in thee are many profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors that make a ſhew of godlineſſe, but deny the power of it; in thee are Lukewarme Chriſtians. Theſe are the ſinnes vnder which the Land groaneth; <hi>Doeſt thou thus requite thy God O fooliſh people?</hi> Shall we not thinke now that the Lord hath a <hi>Controverſie with England? Shall I not viſite for theſe things (ſaith the Lord)? Shall not my ſoule be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this? Let me alone that I may deſtroy them at once. Heare O heavens, hearken O earth, I haue nouriſhed vp chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and they haue rebelled againſt mee: the Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his maſters crib, but my people haue not knowne mee (ſayth the Lord). Ah ſinfull Nation, a people la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with iniquitie, a ſeede of evill doers, why ſhould they be ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten any more, they fall away more and more.</hi> I take no delight to vpbraid mine own Nation, or to defile mine own neſt; but for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake I cannot hold my tongue: let me periſh if I ſee my Country periſh, and giue them not warning. Wherefore I beſeech yee my deare brethren (all true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Engliſhmen)</hi> in the bowells of Chriſt Ieſus, who died for vs, and ſhed his owne heart bloud for vs, as you regard your owne ſoules, bodies, and eſtates; as yee wiſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the peace and proſperity of this our <hi>Sion,</hi> dally with the Lord no longer, God will not be alwayes mocked, turne now at the laſt vnto the Lord with all your hearts; <hi>turne yee, oh turne yee, why will yee die? ſeeke the Lord whileſt he may be found, call vpon him whileſt he is neere; draw neere to God and</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19446:4"/> 
               <hi>he will draw neere to you.</hi> Oh that I could even weepe over this Land, as our Saviour did over <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and ſay: <hi>O England, England, thou that reiecteſt my Prophets, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeſt thoſe that are ſent vnto thee, how often would I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 13. 34.</note> 
               <hi>thee together, as a henne gathereth her chickens vnder her wings, and yee would not;</hi> wherefore thy houſe ſhall be left vnto thee deſolate: <hi>oh that thou wert therefore now wiſe yet in this thy day to conſider thoſe things that belong vnto thy peace, leaſt at length they be hid from thine eyes.</hi> Woe to thee O <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 21.</note> if the great workes which haue beene done in thee, had beene done in <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> in <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> they had repented in ſackcloth and aſhes long ere this: And thou <hi>London, London, which art lifted vp to heaven,</hi> for abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance <note place="margin">23.</note> of ſpirituall meanes, <hi>ſhalt be brought as low as hell,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou repent: wherefore I beſeech yee againe &amp; againe for Chriſts his ſake, for the Goſpels ſake, for your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys ſake, for your owne ſoules ſake be entreated; Repent, repent; <hi>Search, even ſearch your ſelues O nation not worthy to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zeph. 2. 1.</note> 
               <hi>be beloved, before the decree come forth, and yee be as chaffe that paſſeth on a day:</hi> looke into your liues, conſider your wayes, goe apart, and ſeriouſly aske your ſoules; What haue we done? Let your mirth be turned into mourning, your fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting <note place="margin">Dan. 9. 19.</note> into faſting, weepe and lament bitterly for your ſins, cry mightily for mercy, even as for life and death; <hi>ceaſe to doe evill, learne to doe well; waſh you, make you cleane, put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your ſinnes from before God his eyes; rent your hearts and not your garments, amend and change your wayes, bring forth fruits meete for repentance:</hi> that ſo yee may get the ſword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into his ſheath, which is alreadie drawne out, and will giue every one of vs our deaths wound, except we repent; and may quench that wrath which is already kindled, and will burne hotter and hotter, and never ceaſe vntill it haue vtterly conſumed vs, if in time we quench it not by the teares of true repentance: wherefore <hi>now prepare to meete thy God, O England;</hi> It is more then high time to repent, deferre no longer, if the laſt blow be once ſtrucken, that is, <hi>cut it downe,</hi> even vtter deſolation; there will then be left no place
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19446:5"/> for repentance. Oh that I could therefore perſwade you; but it is not I, it is the Lord that muſt doe it; now Lord doe thou perſwade <hi>Iapheth;</hi> for wee cannot: <hi>Turne thou vs vnto thee O Lord of hoſtes, make thy face to ſhine and wee ſhall be ſaved;</hi> convert vs vnto thee, and we ſhall be converted, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new our dayes as of old; Lord thou longeſt for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; thou ſtandeſt waiting and crying; Waſh thine heart, O <hi>England,</hi> wilt thou not be made cleane; oh <hi>when</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 13. 27.</note> 
               <hi>will it once be?</hi> Lord cleanſe thou vs and we ſhall be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; waſh thou vs and we ſhall be whiter then ſnow; cauſe vs to come vnto thee, why haſt thou hardened our hearts from thy feare: O Lord, thou art our Father, we are the clay;
<note place="margin">Iſay. 64. 8.</note> thou art the Potter, we are the worke of thine hands; oh deſtroy not the worke of thine owne hands; frame and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion vs, and make vs ſuch as thou wouldeſt haue vs to be: ſpare thy people, O God, ſpare thy people, and be jealous for thine inheritance, <hi>why ſhall the people ſay; Where is their God? O Lord heare, O Lord forgiue, O Lord conſider, and doe it, deferre not for thy name ſake,</hi> for thy Chriſts his ſake, pittie the deſolations of thy <hi>Sion,</hi> of the Cittie where thy name is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon? Wilt thou O Lord, forſake for ever? <hi>Why is thy wrath thus hot againſt the ſheepe of thy paſture?</hi> Our ſins in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed teſtifie againſt vs, that we are a rebellious &amp; ſtifnecked people, we lye downe in our ſhame, and confuſion cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs; thou art righteous and <hi>iuſt when thou iudgeſt,</hi> but we are a perverſe and froward generation; we would not heare when thou calledſt, but ſtopped our eares, like the deafe Adder, therefore thou maiſt now iuſtly <hi>laugh at our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1. 26. 27</note> 
               <hi>deſtruction, and mocke when our feare commeth:</hi> but there is mercy with thee that thou maiſt be feared, we beſeech thee in wrath remember mercy, haue mercy vpon vs according to the multitude of thy compaſſions, oh Lord ſaue vs or els we periſh. <hi>Comfort vs according to the dayes that thou haſt afflicted vs: Returne O Lord, how long? and be pacified towards thy ſervants.</hi> Continue ſtill to be our God, and let vs be thy people; remoue thy judgements which lye heavie vpon vs, and deſtroy vs not vtterly for thy names ſake: Make vs all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19446:5"/> to turne to thee from the higheſt to the loweſt by ſpeedie and vnfeined repentance, that ſo thou maiſt not vtterly cut vs off, <hi>even head and taile, roote and branch, in one day;</hi> but maiſt ſtill delight to doe vs good, to multiply thy bleſſings vpon vs; and make vs as worthy to be beloved in and through thy Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, that Sonne of thy loue, as we haue beene for our long peace and proſperitie of all the Nations of the earth admired: even ſo be it, Lord ſo be it.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt and generall Remedie which a Nation muſt vſe for the removall and preventing not onely of the Plague, but of any other judgement whatſoever; namely, <hi>true repentance,</hi> which ſtands in ſorrow for ſinne, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation <note place="margin">2 Chron. 7. 13. 14. Ierem. 18. 7. 8. Iſa. 1. 19. 20. Iere. 14. 11. 12</note> of life. <hi>If yee conſent and obey, yee ſhall eate the good fruits of the Land; but if yee refuſe and be rebellious, yee ſhall be devoured with the ſword, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> Now if ſo be I cannot prevaile with the whole Land; then I turne to you that feare the Lord: I hope to haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in your eares. If yee cannot prevaile for others, yet make ſure of your owne ſoules; learne to hide your ſelues, to build an Arke for the ſafetie of you and yours. But yee will ſay, how may that be done? I anſwere.</p>
            <p>1. If yee would not partake with the Plagues of the times, be not pertakers of their ſinnes. <hi>Come out of her my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Revel. 18. 4.</note> 
               <hi>people</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>be yee not partakers of her ſinnes, leaſt yee alſo be partakers of her glagues;</hi> if yee will needs ſinne with them, looke to be plagued with them. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 3, 4. <hi>Thoſe that went with others after Baal peor were deſtroyed, but thoſe that cleaved to the Lord were kept aliue.</hi> Zeph. 2. 3. <hi>Seeke yet the Lord all yee meeke of the earth, which haue wrought his iudgement, ſeeke righteouſneſſe, ſeeke lowlineſſe, if ſo be yee may be hid in the day of the Lord his wrath.</hi> The way to be hid in the day of the Lord his wrath, is <hi>to ſeeke after lowlineſſe,</hi> to carry our ſelues meekly, and to walke humbly, the loweſt ſhrubs are ſafeſt from ſtormes; <hi>to ſeeke after righteouſneſſe,</hi> to walke circumſpectly, and warily, ſhunning the ſinnes of the times, even more then the Plague it ſelfe; to keepe our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19446:6"/> ſelues vnſpotted of the world, to ſaue our ſelues from this froward generation: the infection of ſinne is farre more dangerous then the infection of the Plague; that indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers the body onely, this indangers ſoule and body for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; how ſhould we ſhunne it therefore? How had we need <hi>to abſtaine from all appearance of evill, not onely from the fleſh, but from all the garments ſpotted with the fleſh;</hi> the more wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 22. Iude. 23.</note> the times grow, the more holy we ſhould grow; the more iniquitie abounds, &amp; the loue of many waxeth cold, the more blameleſſe, and zealous in good duties we ſhould ſtriue to be: like bright orient ſtarres, the deeper they goe in the darke night, the brighter they ſhine: thus <hi>Noah</hi> ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his generation. Though <hi>Aegypt</hi> be full of darknes, yet let <hi>Goſhen</hi> be light; though <hi>Iſrael</hi> play the harlot, yet let not <hi>Iudah</hi> ſinne. We are Chriſtians, we profeſſe our <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4. 15. 2 Cor. 6. 14. 15. 16. 17.</note> ſelues to be children of the light, <hi>let not vs</hi> therefore haue any fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull workes of darkneſſe, but reproue them rather: let not fornication or any other vncleanneſſe be once named amongſt vs; let not vs defile our garments. <note place="margin">Revel. 3. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>2. It is not ſufficient that we partake not with the ſinnes of the times, but we muſt mourne for the ſins of the times; we muſt take a view of the abominations committed in <hi>Sion,</hi> and worke our hearts to ſuch a ſorrow as may make <hi>our eyes to guſh out rivers of teares, becauſe men keepe not God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 136.</note> 
               <hi>his law,</hi> then God will wonderfully preſerue vs: <hi>As he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved iuſt Lot out of Sodome, when it was conſumed with fire</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; brimſton from heaven, becauſe his righteous ſoule was vexed from day to day with the vncleane converſation of the Sodomites.</hi> There was <hi>a marke ſet vpon all the true Mourners in Sion,</hi> that when the Angell of the Lord came to ſmite, they might eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape: ſo
<note place="margin">Ezek. 9. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremy,</hi> becauſe <hi>he wiſhed his head a fountaine of teares,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iere. 9. 1.</note> 
               <hi>that he might weepe day and night for the ſinnes of his people;</hi> ſee how the Lord preſerved him alone when all the reſt <note place="margin">Iere. 39. 11. 12</note> were carried into Captivitie: theſe things are written for our learning.</p>
            <p>3. We muſt mourne for our owne ſinnes and labour to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19446:6"/> forſake them. It is ſayd of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> that becauſe his <hi>heart mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 King. 22. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>at the Law read,</hi> both for his owne ſinnes and the ſinnes of his people, <hi>and he humbled his ſoule before the Lord, that therefore he ſhould be put to his graue in peace, and his eyes ſhould not ſee the evill that God would bring vpon the Land.</hi> So if like good <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> our hearts even melt within vs, and we humble our ſoules vnfeinedly before the Lord for our ſinnes, God will worke wonderfully for vs, and we ſhall find gratious experience of his goodneſſe towards vs: <hi>if God ſpared Ahab for his counterfeit humiliation, and would not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King 21. 27. 29.</note> 
               <hi>bring the evill in his dayes;</hi> how much more will he ſpare thoſe that humble their ſoules before him in truth. And as we muſt grieue for our ſinnes, ſo we muſt forſake our ſins: <hi>he that hideth his ſinnes ſhall not proſper,</hi> neither in ſoule nor body, he lyeth open to all dangers; <hi>but he that confeſſeth and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 13.</note> 
               <hi>forſaketh them ſhall find mercy;</hi> God will be mercifull to his ſoule, and preſerue his body: <hi>He that walketh vprightly, walketh ſafely</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon:)</hi> he that laboureth to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of his power to cleare himſelfe from all ſinne, to purge his heart from all hollowneſſe, not cheriſhng any one beloved ſinne, to be vpright in his way; <hi>walking in all the Commandements of God without rebuke;</hi> ſuch a man is a ſafe man, he is ſure nothing can hurt him. It availeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to burne Iuniper, to ſmell to Wormewood, to take ſomwhat in a morning, and to vſe many outward meanes againſt the Plague, ſo long as our ſoules are not ſevered from our ſinnes; it is this inward vncleanneſſe that is the cauſe of that outward, the Plague-ſoare of ſinne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our ſoules are infected, cauſeth the Plague vpon the body: ſever your ſinnes then from your ſoules if ever yee meane to keepe the Plague from your bodies, ſay to theſe menſtrous cloathes; <hi>Get yee hence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly: We muſt truſt in God for ſafety and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; though we may vſe all good and lawfull meanes, yet we muſt not reſt in the meanes, but goe to God for his bleſſing, and depend vpon him for the ſucceſſe. <hi>The Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nahum. 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>is good, and a ſtrong hold in the day of trouble, he knowes all thoſe</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19446:7"/> 
               <hi>that truſt in him; he knowes,</hi> that is, he approues of them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an eſpeciall manner, <hi>He is a ſtrong hold to ſuch in the day of trouble.</hi> Pſal. 33. 18. 19. <hi>Behold the eye of the Lord is vpon them that feare him, and vpon them that truſt in his mercy; to deliver their ſoules from death, &amp; to preſerue them in famine.</hi> Pſal. 91. 1. and ſo forward: <hi>Who ſo dwelleth in the ſecret of the moſt High, ſhall abide vnder the ſhadow of the Almightie; I will ſay vnto the Lord; O my hope and my fortreſſe, he is my God, in him will I truſt: ſurely he will deliver thee from the ſnare of the hunter, and from the noyſome peſtilence. He will cover thee vnder his wings, and thou ſhalt be ſafe vnder his fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; his truth ſhall be thy ſhield and buckler. Thou ſhalt not be afraide of the peſtilence that walketh in the night, nor of the Plague that deſtroyeth at noone day. Thouſands ſhall fall beſide thee, ten thouſands at thy right hand, and yet it ſhall not come nigh thee.</hi> And why all this? <hi>Becauſe thou haſt ſayd, the Lord</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> 
               <hi>is my hope, and haſt ſet the moſt High for thy refuge.</hi> Yee ſee then the wonderfull ſafetie of that man that makes God his confidence. <hi>The name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 18. 10.</note> 
               <hi>runne vnto it, and are exalted.</hi> Great is the ſafetie then of righteous perſons, of ſuch as haue gotten God to be their God in Chriſt, and ſtay their whole affiance in him; God will be vnto them a Tower, a Caſtle, a rocke of defence, a ſafe refuge to fly to in time of neede. He will be their <hi>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 16. 19.</note> 
               <hi>place;</hi> He will keepe them ſafely vnder his wings till <note place="margin">Pſal. 32. 7.</note> the indignation be paſſed over. He hath an Arke for vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Noah,</hi> when he meanes to deſtroy with a vniverſall <note place="margin">Geneſ. 7.</note> Deluge, an whole world of wicked ones. He hath a <hi>Zoar</hi> for righteous <hi>Lot,</hi> when he meanes to conſume filthy <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 19.</note> with fire and brimſtone from heaven. <hi>For the Lord knoweth how to deliver the righteous out of tentation, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 9.</note> 
               <hi>the wicked vnto iudgement.</hi> Therefore I conclude with that of <hi>David.</hi> Pſal. 73. 28. <hi>It is good for me to hold me faſt by God, and to put my truſt in the Lord God:</hi> it is time for the chickens to runne and ſhrowd themſelues vnder the wings of the henne, when the ſtorme begins once to ariſe.</p>
            <p>5. The fift and laſt remedie is, to betake our ſelues to our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19446:7"/> prayers and teares, to cry mightily vnto the Lord, to wraſtle with him, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did: <hi>this is that which holds God his hands from ſmiting:</hi> ſo long as <hi>Moſes</hi> his hand is lifted vp, <hi>Amalek</hi> cannot prevaile. I beſeech yee therefore all yee that wiſh well to this our <hi>Sion,</hi> pray for the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> giue the Lord no reſt, but cry againe and againe, he loues to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned; <hi>the prayer of a righteous man availeth much, if it</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5. 16.</note> 
               <hi>be fervent:</hi> Pray, pray, pray therefore, cry and ſay: <hi>O Lord we know not what to doe, onely our eyes are vp towardes thee: what ſhall we ſay vnto thee O thou preſerver of men; we are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven aſhamed and confounded to lift vp our eyes to heaven;</hi> wee haue ſinned exceedingly, wee, our Rulers and Governors, Prince, and people; we haue all ſinned; our ſinnes are gone vp as an heavy loade, too heavy for vs to beare; heaven and earth even groane vnder the burthen of them, they cry mightily for vengeance, but heare the groanes of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, let their cryes be lowder in thine eares; heare the pleadings and interceſſions of thine owne ſonne for vs; his bloud cryes louder for mercy, then our ſinnes can doe for judgement, had it not beene for that, we had all long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe periſhed, and beene vtterly conſumed. <hi>O thou the hope of Iſrael, the Saviour thereof in the time of trouble, why art thou as a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in the land, as one that paſſeth by to tarry for a night? Why art thou as a man aſtonied, as a ſtrong man that cannot help?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 14. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Yet thou O Lord art in the middeſt of vs, thy name is called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs; forſake vs not. Haſt thou vtterly reiected Iudah? Hath thy ſoule abhorred Sion? Why haſt thou ſmitten vs, that we cannot be healed? We looked for peace, and behold no good; for health, and behold trouble: wee acknowledge O Lord, our wickedneſſe, and the wickedneſſe of our fathers, we haue all ſinned: doe not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre vs for thy names ſake; caſt not downe the throne of thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; remember and breake not thy covenant with vs;</hi> we haue no helpe but of thee, thou art our God, therefore ſaue vs; <hi>oh be favourable vnto thy Sion, build thou the walles of Iereſalem:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſo ſhall we praiſe thy name for ever, and teach all ages to keepe praiſes for thee in ſtore. Oh giue ſalvation to thy people out of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 53. 6.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19446:8"/> 
               <hi>when thou ſhalt reſtore againe the captivitie of thy people, then ſhall I acob reioyce and Iſraell ſhall be glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if ye cannot prevaile for others, yet at leaſt aire your owne houſes with daily and fervent prayers, and that will be a notable meanes to keepe them from the preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: or if it pleaſe God to lay it vpon you notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding yee haue faithfully vſed all theſe meanes: then I dare boldly affirme, yee ſhall finde greater refreſhings <note place="margin">Pſal. 94. 19.</note> from God, then your afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can afford you griefes: howſoever, it will but rid you out of a valley of <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 5.</note> miſery into everlaſting glory. Conſider what I ſay and the Lord giue you vnderſtanding in all things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19446:8"/>
            <head>A Letter full of ſweete Comforts for ſuch as are viſited by the PESTILENCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD the Father of mercies, which hath ſo loved vs to giue his onely Sonne for vs before he gaue vs either chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren or our ſelues, be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto you my deare hearts in the Lord, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>A.</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>A.</hi> my bowells in the Lord: and ſo fill you with his ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant grace, that you may ſay; <hi>It is good for me that I haue beene afflicted; The Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. Iob. 1.</note> 
               <hi>hath given, the Lord hath taken, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>Hearing of the Lords mercifull viſitation of you and yours, I was not a little affected; neither hath any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>loſſe ſince this hand of God hath been on the Cittie,</hi> (though of friends and neere kindred) more pierced my heart with griefe then this of yours. Which ſeeing the Church, which hath called me to a publike Miniſtery, permits me not in preſence privatly to ſignifie, I beſeech God to direct my pen to write ſomwhat for your comfortable applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods correction to your ſoules health. It had much affected me to ſee the ſucceſſion of croſſes in your impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, your wiues long ſickneſſe, with manifold danger of life, &amp;c. And on Thurſday laſt I was very inquiſitiue of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>D.</hi> touching your wife and her delivery: for I had thought ſhee had beene ſent into the country, becauſe ſuch is now the faſhion, and her time of deliverance I thought
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19446:9"/> had beene expired long ſince. But I heard God had ſhewed his power in her weakneſſe, and gaue her (which had long agoe given the ſentence of death vpon her ſelfe) two chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (which the Lord bleſſe and make his owne daughters and heires) before I heard that God had ſmitten one of the former. He gaue two before he would take one, and made her able to beare two at once, which in long time had been ſcarſly able to beare her ſelfe; that he might make his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and his power knowne. He I ſay, to ſhew his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe gaue two for one; yea gaue one for all, his owne Son for our ſelues, and for our ſons and daughters: to purchaſe vs to be <hi>the ſonnes and daughters of the Lord Almightie.</hi> But
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> he gaue him firſt to ſuffer &amp; then to reigne, that he might lead the way to vs; for the ſervant is not greater than his Lord: the ſonne himſelfe learned obedience by the things which he ſuffered. And he that made the world by his Word, was made a man for vs, that he might ſuffer for vs: <note place="margin">Heb. 5. 3.</note> in our nature fulfilled all the righteouſneſſe of God and yet ſuffered all the vnrighteouſneſſe of men, even to that bitter, that ſhameful death of the Croſſe, which God himſelfe had <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 13.</note> myſtically curſed, and he was made a curſe for vs that we might be made heires of bleſſedneſſe. His Croſſe, figured in that tree caſt into the <hi>bitter waters</hi> of <hi>Marah,</hi> takes away <note place="margin">Exod. 15. 25.</note> the curſe from death and all afflictions in vs and ours, and makes them ſweete; doth ſeaſon and ſanctifie them to vs, and vs to them. His preſence doth ſtill change water into <note place="margin">Ioh. 2.</note> wine, if we make him our chiefe gueſt: and (like <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſticke) makes the heavieſt iron to ſwim, the heavieſt heart, <note place="margin">2 King. 6. 6. Pſal. 25. 1. Iob. 19. 25.</note> moſt caſt downe with ſorrow, to ſing, <hi>I lift my heart to thee. I know that my Redeemer liveth,</hi> made <hi>Iob</hi> to liue in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of manifold deaths and ſpoiles, and made him a gainer in &amp; by all his loſſes. Though they aſſailed him all at once, and all the children and ſubſtance which he had gotten all his life before, were in one day taken from him, yet he loſt not himſelfe, by impatience; he bleſſed God which had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him himſelfe, a gift that could not be loſt; and as men in cold windie weather gird their garments cloſer to them,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19446:9"/> ſo he proceeded in courage, and ſaid; <hi>Though he ſlay me yet</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 13. 15. Rom. 15. 4.</note> 
               <hi>will I truſt in him.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe things <hi>are written for our learning, that thorow patience and comfort of the Scriptures we may haue hope.</hi> Yea <hi>tribulation brings forth patience, patience experience,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 3.</note> 
               <hi>experience</hi> (of his deliverance from, or in, manifold trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, as <hi>Davids</hi> deliverance from the Beare and the Lyon, <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.</note> made him bold on the <hi>Philiſtine) experience,</hi> I ſay, <hi>brings forth hope,</hi> even that hope <hi>which never makes aſhamed.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were not in <hi>Canaan</hi> preſently after their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from <hi>Aegypt,</hi> but walked thorow a tedious and irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Wilderneſſe, where was neither harveſt, nor paſture, nor ſweete waters, but their very food and raiment were miraculous proviſion. Yet did not God faile them, and hath promiſed <hi>never to faile nor forſake vs:</hi> he which led <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 5.</note> them by a piller of a cloud and fire, hath given vs his word, <hi>to be with vs to the end of the world.</hi> That hiſtory of the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28. 20.</note> is a myſterie of every true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> his living by faith, as it is often written, the <hi>Iuſt ſhall liue by faith.</hi> We now are travellers thorow the Wilderneſſe of the world to our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and for our ſpirituall life we finde the world as croſſe as they did the <hi>Aegyptians, Amalekites,</hi> and <hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites;</hi> our fleſh is as diſtruſtfull as thoſe which luſted for fleſh in that deſert, and the Devill watcheth all occaſions to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie and rebellion: all that we ſee from our entring the red Sea till we be paſſed over <hi>Iordan</hi> (from Baptiſme to death) is againſt vs: yet our faith lookes on him which is
<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 27. Heb. 11. 1. 1 Ioh. 5. 4. Ephe. 6.</note> inviſible, and is the evidence of things not ſeene. This is the victory that overcometh the world, this is the ſhield which quencheth the fiery darts of hell; to beleeue in Chriſt crucified, that <hi>God hath given him to vs, and for vs, and wtih him all things;</hi> this <hi>crucifieth the fleſh,</hi> with all her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull <hi>lusts</hi> and imaginations; makes vs <hi>deny our ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 24.</note> our wills, our vnderſtandings, husbands, wiues, liues, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, all; and to ſay to God with <hi>David, loe we are here, doe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15. 26.</note> 
               <hi>with vs as ſeemeth good in thine eyes.</hi> Should the Wheat ſay to the husbandman, why doeſt thou wound me with the ſickle, why doeſt thou beat and bruiſe me with the flaile,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19446:10"/> why doeſt thou grind me in the Mill, and put me after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hot Oven? We are Gods wheat, and before we can be manchet for the Lords Table, wee muſt likewiſe paſſe troubles in the fleſh. Yea it is comfortable to vs, becauſe God doth thus ſhew himſelfe <hi>our Father,</hi> and that he doth <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 5. 7. 8.</note> 
               <hi>eſteeme vs as ſonnes,</hi> and not as <hi>baſtards;</hi> for <hi>iudgement here beginneth at Gods houſe:</hi> he doth vs conforme vs to his own <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 17. Rom. 8. 29.</note> ſonne Chriſt; he doth thus prepare vs as ſouldiers by tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and skirmiſhes to the battell with death it ſelfe, yea to the victory, to the crowne; he doth thus ſhew power in weakneſſe, and makes vs conquerors over ſinne and Satan. Neither doe men ſow their corne and ſeeds till the ground <note place="margin">Iere. 4. 3. Mat. 13. 22.</note> be digged or plowed, nor is Gods ſeed like to be profitable till <hi>the fallow of our hearts be turned vp</hi> by the plow or ſpade of affliction. Heaven will make amends for all, and <hi>the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 18.</note> 
               <hi>of this preſent life are not worthy of the glory which ſhall be revealed. Theſe light afflictions</hi> which endure but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>worke out vnto vs that farre moſt excellent and eternall weight of glory.</hi> Courage then, courage my hearts, comfort <note place="margin">2 Cor 4. 17.</note> your ſelues, your Captaine Chriſt lookes on and ſees your ſufferings and fightings in the fleſh; nay he it is which thus trieth you: theſe croſſes are his permiſſion, yea his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, without which no plague can ſtrike a ſtroke <hi>to the pooreſt ſparrow,</hi> no not to the <hi>haires of our head, all which are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 29. 30</note> 
               <hi>numbred:</hi> yea he which ſtriketh vs or ours with his rod knoweth <hi>how to ſuccour them that ſuffer and are tempted,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene tempted himſelfe with greater ſufferings: <hi>he was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2. vlt. Eſa. 53. 4. 5. 6. 2 Cor. 5. 21.</note> 
               <hi>wounded and buiſed, and was made ſin for vs,</hi> before he would wound or buiſe vs for our ſinnes. Yea indeed all theſe blowes are intended to the remainders of ſinne in vs, not to our ſelues, but that the <hi>ſpots</hi> of the <hi>ſoule</hi> may be drawn forth by theſe <hi>Plague-ſpots</hi> on the body, and the <hi>ſinne-ſores</hi> of the <hi>ſoule</hi> may runne and be cut out of theſe <hi>bodily ſores,</hi> that ſin and death (if it proceed ſo farre) may be dead by that our bodily death (that the head of this <hi>Goliah</hi> may be cut off by his owne ſword, and death by death deſtroyed) and our ſoules may eſcape as a bird out of the ſnare of the Fowler,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19446:10"/> and may flee to <hi>their reſt</hi> (not in the Tabernacle like <hi>Davids</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84. Luk. 16. 22.</note> ſparrow, but) <hi>in Gods owne boſome.</hi> As <hi>Lazarus</hi> when none of <hi>Dives</hi> houſhold would come at him, had <hi>Angells</hi> atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him <hi>to carry his ſoule into Abrahams boſome:</hi> ſo when feare and danger (this is part of this chaſtiſement) prohibite others from vs, <hi>he hath given his Angels a charge concerning vs</hi> to convoy our ſoules to heaven, and meane whiles to guard <note place="margin">Pſal 91. 11.</note> their vnregarded bodies on earth. Lift vp the eyes of your faith in beleefe of Gods promiſes, &amp; you ſhall ſee by faith, that which <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſervant did with bodily eyes, the Cittie <note place="margin">2 King. 6.</note> of <hi>London full of Charets and horſes of fire round about every Eliſha.</hi> God himſelfe is the refuge of his ſervants, a houſe to <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. 1.</note> them in this time of grace, a temple to them beyond all times in glory. Come Lord Ieſus to fetch and receiue me to <note place="margin">Apoc. 21.</note> thy ſelfe, and come in what chariot it ſhall pleaſe thee, if in a chariot of fire as thou didſt to <hi>Elias,</hi> or if in infected aire by peſtilent ſtroke; thou that triumphedſt on the Croſſe, over death, hell, and the devill, canſt triumph over my croſſes, and by ſuffering canſt make me triumph alſo over them all. Thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to me by this or any other ſickneſſe or death, is but my paſſage to come to thee: and to goe to Chriſt and ſee him as he is, doth infinitely more then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence
<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 21. 1 Ioh. 3. Rom. 8. 18.</note> all the loſſes, rubbes, and whatſoever irkeſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the way and paſſage. And as for death, we and ours are vaine and mortall, we die daily, our life is but a Candle which in ſhining burneth and waſteth it ſelfe. Me thinkes it is better to haue a ſummons, though by peſtilentiall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, then to be <hi>dead whiles we liue,</hi> as many are which are giddy and drunken with full cups of proſperitie, or whiles <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5. 6. Pro. 1. 32. Luk. 12. Heb. 6. 10.</note> we are ſinging, <hi>Soule take thine eaſe,</hi> ſuddenly to be ſnatched out of the world. <hi>God is not vnfaithfull to forget your free-will offerings</hi> lately to his poore members, he will reward it with a new grant as to <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in his peſtilence with a new
<note place="margin">Eſa. 38.</note> terme of life here; or which is beſt of all, with that life where no plague, nor Devill, nor ſickneſſe, nor death, nor <note place="margin">Apoc. 21.</note> croſſe, nor grievance, ſhall haue poſſibilitie to annoy, where <hi>is fulneſſe of ioy in his preſence, and pleaſures at his right hand</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19446:11"/> 
               <hi>for evermore,</hi> and thoſe ſuch, as <hi>eye hath not ſeene, nor eare heard, nor heart conceived,</hi> where <hi>we ſhall drinke of the River</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 36. 8.</note> 
               <hi>of his pleaſures, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I muſt end, though They doe not. Your viſitation hath not loft <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> gotten all theſe lines, and my daily and more fervent prayer for you and yours to him <hi>who is able to keepe you that you fall not;</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Paſtour, <hi>S. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>REad often <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. and 36. 37. 38. 39. 40. 41. 42. and almoſt all of the <hi>Pſalmes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You haue I thinke the Martyr booke, read the Epiſtles of <hi>Bradford, Hooper, Philpot,</hi> and <hi>Careleſſe:</hi> with innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble others you haue there alſo.</p>
            <p>Read often <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. and the ſtory of Chriſts paſſion. <hi>Eſay</hi> from the fortie Chap. to the end of that booke, being full of ſweete promiſes. Alſo the eight to the <hi>Rom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pray, pray, pray, and <hi>caſt all your care vpon God for he careth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>for you.</hi> With <hi>Peter</hi> agreeth <hi>Paul.</hi> Phil. 4. 6. <hi>Be carefull for nothing, but in every thing by prayer and ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving let your requeſt be made knowne to God.</hi> and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 32. <hi>When we are iudged, we are chaſtened of the Lord, that we ſhould not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned with the world.</hi> It is a ſhort hell which we can haue here, but our heaven will laſt for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>My poore loue will ſcarſly ſuffer me to leaue you, as you ſee by this long writing. But God is all loue; he comes thus to build you, (that is to hew, ſaw, cut with the chiſſell and with all his croſſe-tooles to frame you) to be a dwelling for himſelfe, a temple for his ſpirit, a vine branch to his ſonne, thus purged to bring forth more fruit. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19446:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
